<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, U.S. Geological Survey, and American Wind Energy Association</origin><title>U.S. Wind Turbine Database, Minnesota and National</title><pubinfo><publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20240110</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/util-uswtdb</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This dataset provides locations and technical specifications of wind turbines in the United States, almost all of which are utility-scale. Utility-scale turbines are ones that generate power and feed it into the grid, supplying a utility with energy. They are usually much larger than turbines that would feed a homeowner or business.

&lt;b&gt;The data formats downloadable from the Minnesota Geospatial Commons contain just the Minnesota turbines. Data, maps and services accessed from the USWTDB website provide nationwide turbines.&lt;/b&gt;

The regularly updated database has wind turbine records that have been collected, digitized, and locationally verified. Turbine data were gathered from the Federal Aviation Administration's (FAA) Digital Obstacle File (DOF) and Obstruction Evaluation Airport Airspace Analysis (OE-AAA), the American Wind Energy Association (AWEA), Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory (LBNL), and the United States Geological Survey (USGS), and were merged and collapsed into a single data set.

Verification of the turbine positions was done by visual interpretation using high-resolution aerial imagery in Esri ArcGIS Desktop. A locational error of plus or minus 10 meters for turbine locations was tolerated. Technical specifications for turbines were assigned based on the wind turbine make and models as provided by manufacturers and project developers directly, and via FAA datasets, information on the wind project developer or turbine manufacturer websites, or other online sources. Some facility and turbine information on make and model did not exist or was difficult to obtain. Thus, uncertainty may exist for certain turbine specifications. Similarly, some turbines were not yet built, not built at all, or for other reasons cannot be verified visually. Location and turbine specifications data quality are rated and a confidence is recorded for both. None of the data are field verified.

The U.S. Wind Turbine Database website provides the national data in many different formats:  shapefile, CSV, GeoJSON, web services (cached and dynamic), API, and web viewer. See:  https://eerscmap.usgs.gov/uswtdb/ 

The web viewer provides many options to search; filter by attribute, date and location; and customize the map display. For details and screenshots of these options, see:  https://eerscmap.usgs.gov/uswtdb/help/ 

------------
This metadata record was adapted by the Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo) from the national version of the metadata. It describes the Minnesota extract of the shapefile data that has been projected from geographic to UTM coordinates and converted to Esri file geodatabase (fgdb) format. There may be more recent updates available on the national website. Accessing the data via the national web services or API will always provide the most recent data.</abstract><purpose>The purpose of this information is to provide a regularly updated, publicly available, spatially referenced, national dataset made up almost entirely of utility-scale wind turbine locations and their technical specifications. An appropriate use of the data would be for scientific analysis, research or for general interest for the public. Identification of turbines that have been retrofitted, repowered, decommissioned, and/or removed is a continual ongoing effort; thus, the dataset may contain turbines that were previously verified and subsequently removed.</purpose><supplinf>United States and territories (USWTDB website); Minnesota only (Minnesota Geospatial Commons fgdb and shapefile download)</supplinf></descript><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>utilitiesCommunication, utilities, turbine, energy, renewable, wind turbine, wind farm, wind facility, wind, utility, utilities</themekey></theme><place><placekey>United States, Minnesota</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None.</accconst><useconst>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.

Map services and data downloaded from the U.S. Wind Turbine Database are free and in the public domain. There are no restrictions; however, we request that the following acknowledgment statement be included in products and data derived from our map services when citing, copying, or reprinting: Map services and data are available from U.S. Wind Turbine Database, provided by the U.S. Geological Survey, American Wind Energy Association, and Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory via https://eerscmap.usgs.gov/uswtdb

The full citation for use in academic papers and otherwise where applicable is as follows:
Hoen, B.D., Diffendorfer, J.E., Rand, J.T., Kramer, L.A., Garrity, C.P., Hunt, H.E. (2018) United States Wind Turbine Database. U.S. Geological Survey, American Wind Energy Association, and Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory data release: USWTDB V1.3 (January 7, 2019). https://eerscmap.usgs.gov/uswtdb</useconst><spdom><bounding><westbc>-171.713074</westbc><eastbc>144.722656</eastbc><northbc>66.839905</northbc><southbc>13.389381</southbc></bounding></spdom><timeperd><current>Date of Minnesota extract (fgdb or shapefile) downloadable from the Minnesota Geospatial Commons. For date of web services, viewer or other formats downloadable from the USWTDB website, or to subscribe to update notifications, see:  https://eerscmap.usgs.gov/uswtdb/
November 28, 2023 extract: The latest release includes data on 73,352 turbines covering 43 states (plus Guam and PR). The most recent turbines added to the USWTDB became operational as recently as the second quarter of 2023, with a few from the third quarter of 2023. The oldest turbines in the data set were installed prior to 1990. USWTDB releases generally lag installations by one quarter to allow for merging of the various datasets, visual verification, and quality control.</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20231128</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>In work</progress><update>Unknown</update></status><browse><browsen>https://resources.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_mngeo/util_uswtdb/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen><browsed>Minnesota turbine locations, extracted from the complete U.S. database</browsed></browse><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory</cntorg><cntper>Ben Hoen</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Research Scientist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>20 Sawmill Road</address><city>Milan</city><state>NY</state><postal>12571</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>845-758-1896</cntvoice><cntemail>uswtdb@lbl.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><distinfo><resdesc>U.S. Wind Turbine Database</resdesc><distliab>Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Geological Survey.

Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items for other than personal use must be secured from the copyright owner.

This database has been approved for release and publication by the Director of the USGS. Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on condition that neither the USGS nor the United States Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use.

Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.

While these data are believed to contain correct information, neither the United States Government nor any agency thereof, nor The Regents of the University of California, nor any of their employees, makes any warranty, express or implied, or assumes any legal responsibility for the accuracy, completeness, or usefulness of any information, apparatus, product, or process disclosed, or represents that its use would not infringe privately owned rights. Reference herein to any specific commercial product, process, or service by its trade name, trademark, manufacturer, or otherwise, does not necessarily constitute or imply its endorsement, recommendation, or favoring by the United States Government or any agency thereof, or The Regents of the University of California.

MnGeo's disclaimer:  https://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/disclaimer.html</distliab><stdorder><ordering>The U.S. Wind Turbine Database is available in several ways (an online viewer, several downloadable formats, web map services, and an API) by clicking below after Online Linkage.</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Megan Sisko</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-1240</cntvoice><cntemail>megan.sisko@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20240110</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>https://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Megan Sisko</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-1240</cntvoice><cntemail>megan.sisko@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><dataqual><logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic><complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. It is regularly updated and turbines will be added and removed over time, and characteristics might be altered over time as well. Users should be aware that the location data was based on a snapshot of time; turbines could have been removed after that time or built since the image date. None of the data are field verified.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The wind turbine points were horizontally verified with aerial imagery as specified in the image source attribute. NAIP provides 1 meters ground sample distance orthoimagery to within plus or minus 6 meters to true ground at a 95-percent confidence level. The Bing Maps Aerial basemaps and Digital Globe imagery have a variable resolution and accuracy based on image source, type, and location. The Bing Maps Aerial basemaps horizontal accuracy for CONUS is estimated to be 0.3m to 0.03m. Digital Globe imagery is estimated to be 0.3m to 0.03m.</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><attracc><attraccr>Turbine data points were spatially verified in aerial imagery to confirm or edit their correct position. The map scale used while verifying and digitizing turbines depended on location, need, and imagery availability. Authors used aerial imagery with a typical assessment map scale of 1:2,000 to 1:5,000, none of the spatial verification was done at a map scale smaller than 1:5,000. Uncertainty may exist for certain turbine locations as indicated in confidence turbine location field (t_conf_loc). Uncertainty in turbine specifications was indicated in the confidence of attribute field (t_conf_atr).</attraccr></attracc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>&lt;b&gt;National dataset sources and processing steps:&lt;/b&gt;

The USWTDB combines a 2014 USGS data set (48,956 wind turbines, including decommissioned and duplicate turbines) with a 2017 LBNL data set (43,827 wind turbines) and includes regular updates from AWEA’s WindIQ as well as the Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) Digital Obstacle File (DOF) and Obstacle Evaluation Airport Airspace Analysis (OE-AAA). The USWTDB is updated as frequently as quarterly as new data become available and will lag installations by approximately one quarter.

All turbine points in the data set are visually verified using high-resolution aerial imagery in ESRI ArcGIS Desktop, and X/Y locations are manually moved to the base of the turbine with an estimated locational tolerance of 10 meters. Visual verification also enables identification and removal of duplicate turbine points and decommissioned turbines from the database, although some decommissioned turbines likely have not yet been identified and thus remain in the data set. Moreover, because of a lag in obtaining up-to-date aerial imagery, some turbine locations have not been visually verified.

Technical specifications for turbines are assigned based on turbine make and model as described in literature, specifications listed in the FAA DOF, and collected via AWEA, LBNL, and turbine manufacturer websites. Because some make and model information does not exist or is difficult to obtain, uncertainty may exist for certain turbine specifications.

The uncertainties associated with location and attribute data quality are rated, and a confidence level is recorded. None of the data in the USWTDB are field verified.

See USWTDB metadata for the complete detailed description of data sources and processing steps:  https://eerscmap.usgs.gov/uswtdb/data/ 


&lt;b&gt;Minnesota dataset source and processing steps:&lt;/b&gt;

The most recent shapefile was downloaded from the U.S. Wind Turbine Database website. All turbines in Minnesota (t_state = MN) were selected and saved as a separate file. That file was projected to UTM NAD83 coordinates using Esri's ArcGIS desktop software, then converted to file geodatabase format.

</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>U.S. Wind Turbine Database</enttypl></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>case_id</attrlabl><attrdef>unique uswtdb id</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>faa_ors</attrlabl><attrdef>faa digital obstacle file (dof) for obstacle repository system (ors)</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>faa_asn</attrlabl><attrdef>faa obstruction evaluation - airport airspace analysis (oe-aaa) aeronautical study number (asn)</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>usgs_pr_id</attrlabl><attrdef>usgs id from prior turbine dataset</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_state</attrlabl><attrdef>state where turbine is located</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_county</attrlabl><attrdef>county where turbine is located</attrdef><attrdomv><udom>county where turbine is located</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_fips</attrlabl><attrdef>state and county fips where turbine is located</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>p_name</attrlabl><attrdef>project name</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>p_year</attrlabl><attrdef>year project became operational</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>p_tnum</attrlabl><attrdef>number of turbines in project</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>p_cap</attrlabl><attrdef>project capacity (MW)</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_manu</attrlabl><attrdef>turbine original equipment manufacturer</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_model</attrlabl><attrdef>turbine model</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_cap</attrlabl><attrdef>turbine capacity (kW)</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_hh</attrlabl><attrdef>turbine hub height (meters)</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_rd</attrlabl><attrdef>turbine rotor diameter (meters)</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_rsa</attrlabl><attrdef>turbine rotor swept area (meters^2)</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_ttlh</attrlabl><attrdef>turbine total height - calculated (meters)</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_conf_atr</attrlabl><attrdef>turbine characteristic confidence (0-3)</attrdef><attrdomv><edom><edomv>0</edomv><edomvd>Not verified: attributes have not been verified</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>1</edomv><edomvd>No confidence: no facility data, no name, nothing in publications</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>2</edomv><edomvd>Partial confidence: incomplete information or significant discrepancies across data sources</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>3</edomv><edomvd>Full confidence: consistent information across multiple data sources</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_conf_loc</attrlabl><attrdef>location confidence (0 -3)</attrdef><attrdomv><edom><edomv>0</edomv><edomvd>Not visually verified: Point has not been visually verified yet</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>1</edomv><edomvd>No confidence: No turbine shown in image; image has clouds; imagery older than turbine built date</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>2</edomv><edomvd>Partial confidence: image shows a developed pad with concrete base and/or turbine parts on the ground</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>3</edomv><edomvd>Full confidence: image shows an installed turbine or a tower being constructed; at least partially installed</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_img_date</attrlabl><attrdef>date of image used to visually verify turbine location</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>t_img_srce</attrlabl><attrdef>source of image used to visually verify turbine location</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>xlong</attrlabl><attrdef>longitude (decimal degrees - NAD 83 datum)</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>ylat</attrlabl><attrdef>latitude (decimal degrees - NAD 83 datum)</attrdef></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>Attributes summarized below. For complete details, see the codebook (xls format) at: https://emp.lbl.gov/publications/us-wind-turbine-database-files</eaover></overview></eainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>